<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<elements>
	<info>
		<name>Alignments</name>
		<update version="0.0.5">
			<file name="alignments.xml" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KoenPater/godfall/master/core/players-handbook/alignments.xml" />
		</update>
	</info>

	<element name="Lawful Good" type="Alignment" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_ALIGNMENT_LAWFUL_GOOD">
		<supports>Standard</supports>
		<description>
			<p>The Paragon. A lawful good character acts as a good person is required to act. She combines a selfless commitment to oppose evil with the discipline to fight relentlessly. She tells the truth, keeps her word, helps those in need, and punishes the guilty. A lawful good character favors building and supporting institutions that help protect the innocent.</p>
			<p>Lawful good is the best alignment you can be because it combines honor and compassion.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="standard">true</set>
			<set name="abbreviation">LG</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
	<element name="Neutral Good" type="Alignment" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_ALIGNMENT_NEUTRAL_GOOD">
		<supports>Standard</supports>
		<description>
			<p>The Benefactor. A neutral good character does the best that a good person can do. He is devoted to helping others. He believes in the benefits of just laws and rightful leaders, but does not feel beholden to them.</p>
			<p>Neutral good is the best alignment you can be because it means doing what is good without bias for or against order.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="standard">true</set>
			<set name="abbreviation">NG</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
	<element name="Chaotic Good" type="Alignment" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_ALIGNMENT_CHAOTIC_GOOD">
		<supports>Standard</supports>
		<description>
			<p>The Liberator. A chaotic good character acts as his conscience directs him with little regard for the wishes of society. He fights both for his own freedom and the freedom of others. He is open-minded, compassionate, idealistic, and indepedent. A chaotic good character distrusts instutitions and laws for their ability to corrupt those in power and oppress the innocent.</p>
			<p>Chaotic good is the best alignment you can be because it combines a good heart with a free spirit.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="standard">true</set>
			<set name="abbreviation">CG</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
</elements>