<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<elements>
	<info>
		<name>Ranger</name>
		<description>The Ranger class from the Player’s Handbook.</description>
		<author url="http://dnd.wizards.com/products/tabletop-games/rpg-products/rpg_playershandbook">Wizards of the Coast</author>
		<update version="0.5.6">
			<file name="class-ranger.xml" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KoenPater/godfall/master/core/players-handbook/class-ranger.xml" />
		</update>
	</info>

	<element name="Ranger" type="Class" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_PHB_CLASS_RANGER">
		<description>
			<p class="flavor">Rough and wild looking, a man stalks alone through the shadows of trees, hunting the orcs he knows are planning a raid on a nearby farm. Clutching a shortsword in each hand, he becomes a whirlwind of steel, cutting down one enemy after another.</p>
			<p class="flavor">After tumbling away from a cone of freezing air, a young woman finds her feet and draws back her bow to loose an arrow at the white dragon. Shrugging off the wave of fear that emanates from the dragon, she silently thanks the spirits of the hunt for their aid as she sends one arrow after another to find the gaps between the dragon’s thick scales.</p>			
			<p class="flavor">Holding his hand high, a man whistles to the hawk that circles high above him, calling the bird back to his side. Whispering careful instructions, he points to the owlbear he’s been tracking and sends the hawk to distract the creature while he readies his bow.</p>			
			<p>Far from the bustle of cities and towns, past the hedges that shelter the most distant farms from the terrors of the wild, amid the dense-packed trees of trackless forests and across wide and empty plains, rangers keep their unending watch.</p>
			<h4>DEADLY HUNTERS</h4>
			<p>Warriors of the wilderness, rangers specialize in hunting the monsters that threaten the edges of civilization—humanoid raiders, rampaging beasts and monstrosities, terrible giants, and deadly dragons. They learn to track their quarry as a predator does, moving stealthily through the wilds and hiding themselves in brush and rubble. Rangers focus their combat training on techniques that are particularly useful against their specific favored foes.</p>
			<p class="indent">Thanks to their familiarity with the wilds, rangers acquire the ability to cast spells through the spirits of nature, much as a druid does. Their spells, like their combat abilities, emphasize speed, stealth, and the hunt. A ranger’s talents and abilities are honed with deadly focus on the grim task of protecting the borderlands.</p>
			<h4>INDEPENDENT ADVENTURERS</h4>
			<p>Though a ranger might make a living as a hunter, a guide, or a tracker, a ranger’s true calling is to defend the outskirts of civilization from the ravages of monsters and humanoid hordes that press in from the wild. In some places, rangers gather in secretive orders or join forces with druidic circles. Many rangers, though, are independent almost to a fault, knowing that, when a dragon or a band of orcs attacks, a ranger might be the first—and possibly the last—line of defense.</p>
			<p class="indent">This fierce independence makes rangers well suited to adventuring, since they are accustomed to life far from the comforts of a dry bed and a hot bath. Faced with city-bred adventurers who grouse and whine about the hardships of the wild, rangers respond with some mixture of amusement, frustration, and compassion. But they quickly learn that other adventurers who can carry their own weight in a fight against civilization’s foes are worth any extra burden. Coddled city folk might not know how to feed themselves or find fresh water in the wild, but they make up for it in other ways.</p>
			<h4>CREATING A RANGER</h4>
			<p>As you create your ranger character, consider the nature of the training that gave you your particular capabilities. Did you train with a single mentor, wandering the wilds together until you mastered the ranger’s ways? Did you leave your apprenticeship, or was your mentor slain— perhaps by the same kind of monster that became your favored enemy? Or perhaps you learned your skills as part of a band of rangers affiliated with a druidic circle, trained in mystic paths as well as wilderness lore. You might be self-taught, a recluse who learned combat skills, tracking, and even a magical connection to the spirits of nature through the necessity of surviving in the wilds.</p>
			<p class="indent">What’s the source of your particular hatred of a certain kind of enemy? Did a monster kill someone you loved or destroy your home village? Or did you see too much of the destruction these monsters cause and commit yourself to reining in their depredations? Is your adventuring career a continuation of your work in protecting the borderlands, or a significant change? What made you join up with a band of adventurers? Do you find it challenging to teach new allies the ways of the wild, or do you welcome the relief from solitude that they offer?</p>
			<h5>QUICK BUILD</h5>
			<p>You can make a ranger quickly by following these suggestions. First, make Dexterity your highest ability score, followed by Wisdom. (Some rangers who focus on two-weapon fighting make Strength higher than Dexterity.) Second, choose the outlander background.</p>
			<h3>CLASS FEATURES</h3>
			<p>As a ranger, you gain the following class features.</p>
            <h5>HIT POINTS</h5>
            <ul class="unstyled">
                <li><strong>Hit Dice:</strong> 1d10 per ranger level</li>
                <li><strong>Hit Points at 1st Level:</strong> 10 + your Constitution modifier</li>
                <li><strong>Hit Points at Higher Levels:</strong> 1d10 (or 6) + your Constitution modifier per ranger level after 1st</li>
            </ul>
            <h5>PROFICIENCIES</h5>
            <ul class="unstyled mb">
                <li><strong>Armor:</strong> Light armor, medium armor, shields</li>
                <li><strong>Weapons:</strong> Simple weapons, martial weapons</li>
                <li><strong>Tools:</strong> None</li>
            </ul>
            <ul class="unstyled">
                <li><strong>Saving Throws:</strong> Strength, Dexterity</li>
                <li><strong>Skills:</strong> Choose three skills from Animal Handling, Athletics, Insight, Investigation, Nature, Perception, Stealth, and Survival</li>
            </ul>
			<h5>EQUIPMENT</h5>
			<p>You start with the following equipment, in addition to the equipment granted by your background:</p>
			<ul>
				<li> <i>(a)</i> scale mail or <i>(b)</i> leather armor </li>
				<li> <i>(a)</i> two shortswords or <i>(b)</i> two simple melee weapons </li>
				<li> <i>(a)</i> a dungeoneer’s pack or <i>(b)</i> an explorer’s pack </li>
				<li>A longbow and a quiver of 20 arrows</li>
			</ul>
			<h5 class="caption">THE RANGER</h5>
			<table class="class-features">
				<thead>
					<tr><td class="col-5">Level</td><td class="left">Features</td><td class="col-10">Spells Known</td><td>1st</td><td>2nd</td><td>3rd</td><td>4th</td><td>5th</td></tr>
				</thead>
				<tr><td> 1st</td><td class="left">Favored Enemy, Natural Explorer</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>—</td></tr>
				<tr><td> 2nd</td><td class="left">Fighting Style, Spellcasting</td><td>2</td><td>2</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>—</td></tr>
				<tr><td> 3rd</td><td class="left">Ranger Archetype, Primeval Awareness</td><td>3</td><td>3</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>—</td></tr>
				<tr><td> 4th</td><td class="left">Ability Score Improvement</td><td>3</td><td>3</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>—</td></tr>
				<tr><td> 5th</td><td class="left">Extra Attack, Additional Fighting Style</td><td>4</td><td>4</td><td>2</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>—</td></tr>
				<tr><td> 6th</td><td class="left">Favored Enemy and Natural Explorer improvements</td><td>5</td><td>4</td><td>2</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>—</td></tr>
				<tr><td> 7th</td><td class="left">Ranger Archetype feature</td><td>6</td><td>4</td><td>3</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>—</td></tr>
				<tr><td> 8th</td><td class="left">Ability Score Improvement, Land’s Stride</td><td>6</td><td>4</td><td>3</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>—</td></tr>
				<tr><td> 9th</td><td class="left">—</td><td>7</td><td>4</td><td>3</td><td>2</td><td>—</td><td>—</td></tr>
				<tr><td>10th</td><td class="left">Natural Explorer improvement, Nature`s Veil</td><td>8</td><td>4</td><td>3</td><td>2</td><td>—</td><td>—</td></tr>
				<tr><td>11th</td><td class="left">Ranger Archetype feature</td><td>9</td><td>4</td><td>3</td><td>3</td><td>—</td><td>—</td></tr>
				<tr><td>12th</td><td class="left">Ability Score Improvement</td><td>9</td><td>4</td><td>3</td><td>3</td><td>—</td><td>—</td></tr>
				<tr><td>13th</td><td class="left">Tireless</td><td>10</td><td>4</td><td>3</td><td>3</td><td>1</td><td>—</td></tr>
				<tr><td>14th</td><td class="left">Ability Score Improvement</td><td>11</td><td>4</td><td>3</td><td>3</td><td>1</td><td>—</td></tr>
				<tr><td>15th</td><td class="left">Ranger Archetype feature, Favored Enemy improvement</td><td>12</td><td>4</td><td>3</td><td>3</td><td>2</td><td>—</td></tr>
				<tr><td>16th</td><td class="left">Ability Score Improvement</td><td>12</td><td>4</td><td>3</td><td>3</td><td>2</td><td>—</td></tr>
				<tr><td>17th</td><td class="left">—</td><td>13</td><td>4</td><td>3</td><td>3</td><td>3</td><td>1</td></tr>
				<tr><td>18th</td><td class="left">Feral Senses</td><td>14</td><td>4</td><td>3</td><td>3</td><td>3</td><td>1</td></tr>
				<tr><td>19th</td><td class="left">Ability Score Improvement</td><td>14</td><td>4</td><td>3</td><td>3</td><td>3</td><td>2</td></tr>
				<tr><td>20th</td><td class="left">Foe Slayer</td><td>15</td><td>4</td><td>3</td><td>3</td><td>3</td><td>2</td></tr>
			</table>
			<div element="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY" />
			<div element="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_NATURAL_EXPLORER" />
			<div element="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_FIGHTING_STYLE" />
			<div element="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_SPELLCASTING" />
			<div element="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_RANGER_ARCHETYPE" />
			<div element="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_PRIMEVAL_AWARENESS" />
			<div element="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_ASI" />
			<div element="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_EXTRA_ATTACK" />
			<div element="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_LANDS_STRIDE" />
			<div element="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_HIDE_IN_PLAIN_SIGHT" />
			<div element="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_VANISH" />
			<div element="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_FERAL_SENSES" />
			<div element="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_FOE_SLAYER" />
		</description>
		<sheet display="false">
			<description>A warrior who uses martial prowess and nature magic to combat threats on the edges of civilization.</description>
		</sheet>
		<setters>
			<set name="short">A warrior who uses martial prowess and nature magic to combat threats on the edges of civilization.</set>
			<set name="hd">d10</set>
		</setters>
		<rules>
			<grant type="Proficiency" id="ID_PROFICIENCY_ARMOR_PROFICIENCY_LIGHT_ARMOR" requirements="!ID_WOTC_PHB_MULTICLASS_RANGER" />
			<grant type="Proficiency" id="ID_PROFICIENCY_ARMOR_PROFICIENCY_MEDIUM_ARMOR" requirements="!ID_WOTC_PHB_MULTICLASS_RANGER" />
			<grant type="Proficiency" id="ID_PROFICIENCY_ARMOR_PROFICIENCY_SHIELDS" requirements="!ID_WOTC_PHB_MULTICLASS_RANGER" />
			<grant type="Proficiency" id="ID_PROFICIENCY_WEAPON_PROFICIENCY_SIMPLE_WEAPONS" requirements="!ID_WOTC_PHB_MULTICLASS_RANGER" />
			<grant type="Proficiency" id="ID_PROFICIENCY_WEAPON_PROFICIENCY_MARTIAL_WEAPONS" requirements="!ID_WOTC_PHB_MULTICLASS_RANGER" />
			<grant type="Proficiency" id="ID_PROFICIENCY_SAVINGTHROW_STRENGTH" requirements="!ID_WOTC_PHB_MULTICLASS_RANGER" />
			<grant type="Proficiency" id="ID_PROFICIENCY_SAVINGTHROW_DEXTERITY" requirements="!ID_WOTC_PHB_MULTICLASS_RANGER" />
			<select type="Proficiency" name="Skill Proficiency (Ranger)" supports="Skill,Ranger" number="3" requirements="!ID_WOTC_PHB_MULTICLASS_RANGER" />
			<grant type="Class Feature" id="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY" level="1"/>
			<grant type="Class Feature" id="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_NATURAL_EXPLORER" level="1"/>
			<grant type="Class Feature" id="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_FIGHTING_STYLE" level="2"/>
			<grant type="Class Feature" id="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_SPELLCASTING" level="2"/>
			<grant type="Class Feature" id="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_RANGER_ARCHETYPE" level="3"/>
			<grant type="Class Feature" id="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_PRIMEVAL_AWARENESS" level="3"/>
			<grant type="Class Feature" id="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_ASI" level="4"/>
			<grant type="Class Feature" id="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_EXTRA_ATTACK" level="5"/>
			<grant type="Class Feature" id="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_ADDITIONALFIGHTINGSTYLE" level="5"/>
			<grant type="Class Feature" id="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_LANDS_STRIDE" level="8"/>
			<grant type="Class Feature" id="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_HIDE_IN_PLAIN_SIGHT" level="10"/>
			<grant type="Class Feature" id="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_VANISH" level="13"/>
			<grant type="Class Feature" id="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_FERAL_SENSES" level="18"/>
			<grant type="Class Feature" id="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_FOE_SLAYER" level="20"/>
		</rules>
		<multiclass id="ID_WOTC_PHB_MULTICLASS_RANGER">
			<prerequisite>Dexterity 13 and Wisdom 13</prerequisite>
			<requirements>([dex:13],[wis:13])</requirements>
			<setters>
				<set name="multiclass proficiencies">Light armor, medium armor, shields, simple weapons, martial weapons, one skill from the class’s skill list</set>
			</setters>
			<rules>
				<grant type="Grants" id="ID_INTERNAL_GRANT_MULTICLASS" />
				<grant type="Proficiency" id="ID_PROFICIENCY_ARMOR_PROFICIENCY_LIGHT_ARMOR" />
				<grant type="Proficiency" id="ID_PROFICIENCY_ARMOR_PROFICIENCY_MEDIUM_ARMOR" />
				<grant type="Proficiency" id="ID_PROFICIENCY_ARMOR_PROFICIENCY_SHIELDS" />
				<grant type="Proficiency" id="ID_PROFICIENCY_WEAPON_PROFICIENCY_SIMPLE_WEAPONS" />
				<grant type="Proficiency" id="ID_PROFICIENCY_WEAPON_PROFICIENCY_MARTIAL_WEAPONS" />
				<select type="Proficiency" name="Skill Proficiency (Ranger)" supports="Skill,Ranger" number="1"/>
			</rules>
		</multiclass>
	</element>
	<element name="Favored Enemy" type="Class Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY">
		<description>
			<p>Beginning at 1st level, you have significant experience studying, tracking, hunting, and even talking to a certain type of enemy.</p>
			<p class="indent">Choose a type of favored enemy: beasts, fey, monstrosities, or undead. Alternatively, you can select two races of humanoid (such as gnolls and orcs) as favored enemies.</p>
			<p class="indent">You add your Wisdom modifier to damage rolls with weapon attacks against creatures of the chosen type, in addition to your normal ability modifier.</p>
			<p class="indent">Additionally, you have advantage on Wisdom (Survival) checks to track your favored enemies, as well as on Intelligence checks to recall information about them.</p>
			<p class="indent">When you gain this feature, you also learn one language of your choice that is spoken by your favored enemies, if they speak one at all.</p>
			<p class="indent">You choose one additional favored enemy, as well as an associated language, at 6th and 15th level. At these levels, you may also select your favored enemy from among aberrations, celestials, constructs, or elementals. As you gain levels, your choices should reflect the types of monsters you have encountered on your adventures.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>You deal {{wisdom:modifier}} additional damage against your favored enemies. You also have advantage on Survival checks to track them, as well as on Intelligence checks to recall information about them.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<select type="Class Feature" name="Favored Enemy" supports="Favored Enemy,Basic" level="1" />
			<select type="Class Feature" name="Favored Enemy" supports="Favored Enemy" level="6" />
			<select type="Class Feature" name="Favored Enemy" supports="Favored Enemy" level="15" />			
			<select type="Class Feature" name="Favored Enemy, Humanoid" supports="Humanoid Favored Enemy" number="2" level="1" requirements="ID_WOTC_PHB_CLASS_FEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_HUMANOIDS_1" />
			<select type="Class Feature" name="Favored Enemy, Humanoid" supports="Humanoid Favored Enemy" number="2" level="6" requirements="ID_WOTC_PHB_CLASS_FEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_HUMANOIDS_2" />
			<select type="Class Feature" name="Favored Enemy, Humanoid" supports="Humanoid Favored Enemy" number="2" level="15" requirements="ID_WOTC_PHB_CLASS_FEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_HUMANOIDS_3" />
			<select type="Language" name="Language (Favored Enemy)" optional="true" level="1" requirements="ID_WOTC_PHB_CLASS_FEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_HUMANOIDS_1" />
			<select type="Language" name="Language (Favored Enemy)" optional="true" level="6" requirements="ID_WOTC_PHB_CLASS_FEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_HUMANOIDS_2" />
			<select type="Language" name="Language (Favored Enemy)" optional="true" level="15" requirements="ID_WOTC_PHB_CLASS_FEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_HUMANOIDS_3" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Natural Explorer" type="Class Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_NATURAL_EXPLORER">
		<description>
			<p>You are particularly familiar with one type of natural environment and are adept at traveling and surviving in such regions. You gain the following benefits while in your favored terrain:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>You gain advantage on initiative rolls.</li>
				<li>You gain advantage on Dexterity saving throws.</li>
				<li>When you make an ability check related to the terrain, your proficiency bonus is doubled if you are using a skill that you’re proficient in.</li>
			</ul>
			<p class="indent">In addition, while traveling for an hour or more in your favored terrain, you also gain the following benefits:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>Difficult terrain doesn’t slow your group’s travel.</li>
				<li>Your group can’t become lost except by magical means.</li>
				<li>Even when you are engaged in another activity while traveling (such as foraging, navigating, or tracking), you remain alert to danger.</li>
				<li>If you are traveling alone, you can move stealthily at a normal pace.</li>
				<li>When you forage, you find twice as much food as you normally would.</li>
				<li>While tracking other creatures, you also learn their exact number, their sizes, and how long ago they passed through the area.</li>
			</ul>
			<p class="indent">You choose additional favored terrain types at 6th and 10th level.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>While in your favored terrain, you gain advantage on initiative rolls and Dexterity saving throws. You also double any proficiency bonus added to ability checks related to the terrain. In addition, while traveling for an hour or more in your favored terrain, you also gain the following benefits: Difficult terrain doesn’t slow your group’s travel. Your group can’t become lost except by magical means. Even when you are engaged in another activity while traveling, you remain alert to danger. If you are traveling alone, you can move stealthily at a normal pace. When you forage, you find twice as much food as you normally would. If you successfully track other creatures, you also learn their exact number, their sizes, and how long ago they passed through the area.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<select type="Class Feature" name="Favored Terrain" supports="Favored Terrain" level="1" />
			<select type="Class Feature" name="Favored Terrain" supports="Favored Terrain" level="6" />
			<select type="Class Feature" name="Favored Terrain" supports="Favored Terrain" level="10" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Fighting Style" type="Class Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_FIGHTING_STYLE">
		<description>
			<p>At 2nd level, you adopt a particular style of fighting as your specialty. Choose one of the following options. You can’t take a Fighting Style option more than once, even if you later get to choose again.</p>
			<h5 class="caption">ARCHERY</h5>
			<p>You gain a +2 bonus to attack rolls you make with ranged weapons.</p>
			<h5 class="caption">DEFENSE</h5>
			<p>While you are wearing armor, you gain a +1 bonus to AC.</p>
			<h5 class="caption">VERSATILE</h5>
			<p>When you are wielding a one-handed melee weapon in one hand and no other weapons or shields, you gain a +2 bonus to attack rolls. When you are wielding a one-handed melee weapon with two hands, you gain a +1 bonus to damage rolls.</p>
			<h5 class="caption">TWO-WEAPON FIGHTING</h5>
			<p>When you engage in two-weapon fighting, you can add your ability modifier to the damage of the second attack.</p>
		</description>
		<rules>
			<select type="Class Feature" name="Fighting Style" supports="Fighting Style,Ranger" level="2"/>
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Additional Fighting Style" type="Class Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_ADDITIONALFIGHTINGSTYLE">
		<description>
			<p>At 5th level, you can choose a second option from the Fighting Style class feature.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>You adopt a second style of fighting as your specialty.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<select type="Class Feature" name="Additional Fighting Style" supports="Fighting Style,Ranger" level="5"/>
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Spellcasting" type="Class Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_SPELLCASTING">
		<description>
			<p>By the time you reach 2nd level, you have learned to use the magical essence of nature to cast spells, much as a druid does. See chapter 10 for the general rules of spellcasting and chapter 11 for the ranger spell list.</p>
			<h5>SPELL SLOTS</h5>
			<p>The Ranger table shows how many spell slots you have to cast your ranger spells of 1st level and higher. To cast one of these spells, you must expend a slot of the spell’s level or higher. You regain all expended spell slots when you finish a long rest.</p>
			<p class="indent">For example, if you know the 1st-level spell animal friendship and have a 1st-level and a 2nd-level spell slot available, you can cast animal friendship using either slot.</p>
			<h5>SPELLS KNOWN OF 1ST LEVEL AND HIGHER</h5>
			<p>You know two 1st-level spells of your choice from the ranger spell list.</p>
			<p class="indent">The Spells Known column of the Ranger table shows when you learn more ranger spells of your choice. Each of these spells must be of a level for which you have spell slots. For instance, when you reach 5th level in this class, you can learn one new spell of 1st or 2nd level.</p>
			<p class="indent">Additionally, when you gain a level in this class, you can choose one of the ranger spells you know and replace it with another spell from the ranger spell list, which also must be of a level for which you have spell slots.</p>
			<h5>SPELLCASTING ABILITY</h5>
			<p>Wisdom is your spellcasting ability for your ranger spells, since your magic draws on your attunement to the natural spirits. You use your Wisdom whenever a spell refers to your spellcasting ability. In addition, you use your Wisdom modifier when setting the saving throw DC for a ranger spell you cast and when making an attack roll with one.</p>
			<center>
				<p><strong>Spell save DC</strong> = 8 + your proficiency bonus + your Wisdom modifier</p>
				<p><strong>Spell attack modifier</strong> = your proficiency bonus + your Wisdom modifier</p>
			</center>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false">
			<description>You have learned to use the magical essence of nature to cast spells, much as a druid does.</description>
		</sheet>
		<spellcasting name="Ranger" ability="Wisdom" allowReplace="true">
			<list>Ranger</list>
		</spellcasting>
		<rules>
			<grant type="Grants" id="ID_INTERNAL_GRANT_MULTICLASS_SPELLCASTING_SLOTS_HALF" requirements="ID_INTERNAL_GRANT_MULTICLASS"/>
			<stat name="ranger:spellcasting:slots:1" value="2" level="2" />
			<stat name="ranger:spellcasting:slots:1" value="1" level="3" />
			<stat name="ranger:spellcasting:slots:1" value="1" level="5" />
			<stat name="ranger:spellcasting:slots:2" value="2" level="5" />
			<stat name="ranger:spellcasting:slots:2" value="1" level="7" />
			<stat name="ranger:spellcasting:slots:3" value="2" level="9" />
			<stat name="ranger:spellcasting:slots:3" value="1" level="11" />
			<stat name="ranger:spellcasting:slots:4" value="1" level="13" />
			<stat name="ranger:spellcasting:slots:4" value="1" level="15" />
			<stat name="ranger:spellcasting:slots:4" value="1" level="17" />
			<stat name="ranger:spellcasting:slots:5" value="1" level="17" />
			<stat name="ranger:spellcasting:slots:5" value="1" level="19" />
			<select type="Spell" name="Spellcasting (Ranger)" supports="$(spellcasting:list),$(spellcasting:slots)" level="2" number="2" spellcasting="Ranger"/>
			<select type="Spell" name="Spellcasting (Ranger)" supports="$(spellcasting:list),$(spellcasting:slots)" level="3" spellcasting="Ranger" />
			<select type="Spell" name="Spellcasting (Ranger)" supports="$(spellcasting:list),$(spellcasting:slots)" level="5" spellcasting="Ranger" />
			<select type="Spell" name="Spellcasting (Ranger)" supports="$(spellcasting:list),$(spellcasting:slots)" level="6" spellcasting="Ranger" />
			<select type="Spell" name="Spellcasting (Ranger)" supports="$(spellcasting:list),$(spellcasting:slots)" level="7" spellcasting="Ranger" />
			<select type="Spell" name="Spellcasting (Ranger)" supports="$(spellcasting:list),$(spellcasting:slots)" level="9" spellcasting="Ranger" />
			<select type="Spell" name="Spellcasting (Ranger)" supports="$(spellcasting:list),$(spellcasting:slots)" level="10" spellcasting="Ranger" />
			<select type="Spell" name="Spellcasting (Ranger)" supports="$(spellcasting:list),$(spellcasting:slots)" level="11" spellcasting="Ranger" />
			<select type="Spell" name="Spellcasting (Ranger)" supports="$(spellcasting:list),$(spellcasting:slots)" level="13" spellcasting="Ranger" />
			<select type="Spell" name="Spellcasting (Ranger)" supports="$(spellcasting:list),$(spellcasting:slots)" level="14" spellcasting="Ranger" />
			<select type="Spell" name="Spellcasting (Ranger)" supports="$(spellcasting:list),$(spellcasting:slots)" level="15" spellcasting="Ranger" />
			<select type="Spell" name="Spellcasting (Ranger)" supports="$(spellcasting:list),$(spellcasting:slots)" level="17" spellcasting="Ranger" />
			<select type="Spell" name="Spellcasting (Ranger)" supports="$(spellcasting:list),$(spellcasting:slots)" level="18" spellcasting="Ranger" />
			<select type="Spell" name="Spellcasting (Ranger)" supports="$(spellcasting:list),$(spellcasting:slots)" level="20" spellcasting="Ranger" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Ranger Archetype" type="Class Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_RANGER_ARCHETYPE">
		<description>
			<p>At 3rd level, you choose an archetype that you strive to emulate: Hunter or Beast Master, both detailed at the end of the class description. Your choice grants you features at 3rd level and again at 7th, 11th, and 15th level.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<rules>
			<select type="Archetype" name="Ranger Archetype" supports="Ranger Archetype" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Primeval Awareness" type="Class Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_PRIMEVAL_AWARENESS">
		<description>
			<p>Beginning at 3rd level, you can use your action and expend one ranger spell slot to focus your awareness on the region around you. For the next 10 minutes, you can sense whether the following types of creatures are present within a number of miles equal to the level of the spell slot you expended (or three times that distance if you are in your Favored terrain): Aberrations, Celestials, Elementals, Fey, and Undead. In addition, these creature types cannot surprise you, nor can they gain advantage on attack rolls against you as a result of being unseen. This feature doesn't reveal the creatures' exact location or number, though it might give a decent estimation.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet action="Action">
			<description>You must expend one ranger spell slot to use this feature. For the next 10 minutes, you can sense whether the following types of creatures are present within a number of miles equal to the level of the spell slot you expended (or three times that distance if you are in your Favored terrain): Aberrations, Celestials, Elementals, Fey, and Undead. In addition, these creature types cannot surprise you, nor can they gain advantage on attack rolls against you as a result of being unseen. This feature doesn't reveal the creatures' exact location or number, though it might give a decent estimation.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Ability Score Improvement" type="Class Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_ASI">
		<compendium display="false" />
		<description>
			<p>When you reach 4th level, and again at 8th, 12th, 14th, 16th, and 19th level, you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature. Alternatively, if your DM allows it, you can take one feat of your choice instead.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<rules>
			<select type="Class Feature" name="Improvement Option (Ranger 4)" supports="Improvement Option,Ranger,4" level="4" />
			<select type="Class Feature" name="Improvement Option (Ranger 8)" supports="Improvement Option,Ranger,8" level="8" />
			<select type="Class Feature" name="Improvement Option (Ranger 12)" supports="Improvement Option,Ranger,12" level="12" />
			<select type="Class Feature" name="Improvement Option (Ranger 14)" supports="Improvement Option,Ranger,14" level="14" />			
			<select type="Class Feature" name="Improvement Option (Ranger 16)" supports="Improvement Option,Ranger,16" level="16" />
			<select type="Class Feature" name="Improvement Option (Ranger 19)" supports="Improvement Option,Ranger,19" level="19" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Extra Attack" type="Class Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_EXTRA_ATTACK">
		<description>
			<p>Beginning at 5th level, you can attack twice, instead of once, whenever you take the Attack action on your turn.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>You can attack twice, instead of once, whenever you take the Attack action on your turn.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<stat name="extra attack:count" value="2" level="5" bonus="extra attack" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Land’s Stride" type="Class Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_LANDS_STRIDE">
		<description>
			<p>Starting at 8th level, moving through difficult terrain costs you no extra movement. You also have resistance against any piercing or slashing damage caused by moving through terrain.</p>
			<p class="indent">Lastly, you have advantage on saving throws against plants that are magically created or manipulated to impede movement, such those created by the entangle spell.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>Moving through difficult terrain costs you no extra movement. You also have resistance against any piercing or slashing damage caused by moving through terrain. You have advantage on saving throws against plants that are magically created or manipulated to impede movement, such those created by the entangle spell.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Nature's Veil" type="Class Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_HIDE_IN_PLAIN_SIGHT">
		<description>
			<p>Starting at 10th level, you can draw on the powers of nature to briefly hide yourself from view. As a bonus action, you can magically become <em>invisible</em>, along with any equipment you are wearing or carrying, until the start of your next turn. If you are in your favored terrain, the invisibility lasts one additional turn (for a total of two turns).</p>
			<p class="indent">Once you use this feature, you must finish a short or long rest before you can use it again.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet usage="1/Short Rest" action="Bonus Action">
			<description>Become invisible until the start of your next turn. Lasts one additional turn in your favored terrain.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Tireless" type="Class Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_VANISH">
		<description>
			<p>Starting at 13th level, you can draw upon primal forces to fuel your journeys. Whenever you finish a short or long rest, you gain the following benefits:</p>
			<ul>
			  <li>You gain temporary hit points equal to 1d12 + your Wisdom modifier. When resting in your favored terrain you can take the maximum result of the roll.</li>
			  <li>In addition you can make a DC 10 Wisdom ability check. If you succeed, you can either remove one level of exhaustion or recover an expended 1st level spell slot.</li>
			</ul>
		</description>
		<sheet use="Short Rest">
			<description>After finishing a short or long rest, gain 1d12 + {{wisdom:modifier}} temporary hit points, or {{temphp:amount}} in your favored terrain. Make a Wisdom check (DC 10) to recover one level of exhaustion or one 1st level spell slot.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<stat name="temphp:amount" value="12" />
			<stat name="temphp:amount" value="wisdom:modifier" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Feral Senses" type="Class Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_FERAL_SENSES">
		<description>
			<p>At 18th level, your heightened attunement to the world around you grants you Blindsight with a range of 30 feet.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>You have Blindsight with a range of 30 feet.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Foe Slayer" type="Class Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_FOE_SLAYER">
		<description>
			<p>At 20th level, you become an unparalleled hunter of your enemies. You learn the <i>Hunter's Mark</i> spell. This spell no longer requires Concentration when you cast it. In addition, once per turn you may reroll a failed attack roll made against the target of your <i>Hunter's Mark</i>.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description><i>Hunter's Mark</i> no longer requires Concentration. Once per turn you may reroll a failed attack roll made against the target of your <i>Hunter's Mark</i>.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Aberrations" type="Class Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_ABERRATIONS">
		<supports>Favored Enemy,Monster Type</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Aberrations are utterly unnatural beings. Many of them have innate magical abilities drawn from the creature’s alien mind or a perversion of the mystical forces of the world. The quintessential aberrations are aboleths, beholders, mind fiayers, oozes, and slaadi.</p>
		</description>
	</element>
	<element name="Beasts" type="Class Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_BEAST">
		<supports>Favored Enemy,Monster Type,Basic</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Beasts are nonhumanoid creatures that are a natural part of the world. Some of them have powers that border on the magical, but most are unintelligent and lack any society or language. Beasts include all varieties of animals, as well as more fantastical beasts such as ankhegs, griffons, and dire wolves.</p>
		</description>		
	</element>
	<element name="Celestials" type="Class Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_CELESTIALS">
		<supports>Favored Enemy,Monster Type</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Celestials are creatures native to the Empyrean otherworld. Many of them were the servants of the gods, employed as messengers or agents in the mortal realm and beyond. Celestials include archons, couatls, pegasi, and the fallen.</p>
		</description>		
	</element>
	<element name="Constructs" type="Class Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_CONSTRUCTS">
		<supports>Favored Enemy,Monster Type</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Constructs are animated beings. Some are made by their creators to follow a simple set of instructions, while others are imbued with sentience and capable of independent thought. Golems are the iconic constructs, as are gargoyles.</p>
		</description>		
	</element>
	<element name="Dragons" type="Class Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_DRAGONS">
		<requirements>ID_GODS_LIVING</requirements>
		<compendium display="false" />
		<supports>Favored Enemy,Monster Type</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Dragons are large reptilian creatures of ancient origin and tremendous power. True dragons, including the good metallic dragons and the evil chromatic dragons, are highly intelligent and have innate magic. Also in this category are creatures distantly related to true dragons, but less powerful, less intelligent, and less magical, such as wyverns and pseudodragons.</p>
		</description>		
	</element>
	<element name="Elementals" type="Class Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_ELEMENTALS">
		<supports>Favored Enemy,Monster Type</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Elementals are creatures native to the elemental chaos beyond our world. Some creatures of this type are little more than animate masses of their respective elements, including the creatures simply called elementals. Others have biological forms infused with elemental energy. The perverted creatures known as demons are also elemental in origin.</p>
		</description>		
	</element>
	<element name="Fey" type="Class Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_FEY">
		<supports>Favored Enemy,Monster Type,Basic</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Fey are magical creatures closely tied to the forces of nature. They dwell in twilight groves and misty forests of our world, though they often find their origin in the Feywild. Fey include centaurs, dryads, hags, and satyrs.</p>
		</description>		
	</element>
	<element name="Fiends" type="Class Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_FIENDS">
		<requirements>ID_GODS_LIVING</requirements>
		<compendium display="false" />
		<supports>Favored Enemy,Monster Type</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Fiends are creatures of wickedness that are native to the Lower Planes. A few are the servants of deities, but many more labor under the leadership of archdevils and demon princes. Evil priests and mages sometimes summon fiends to the material world to do their bidding. If an evil celestial is a rarity, a good fiend is almost inconceivable. Fiends include demons, devils, hell hounds, rakshasas, and yugoloths.</p>
		</description>		
	</element>
	<element name="Giants" type="Class Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_GIANTS">
		<requirements>ID_GODS_LIVING</requirements>
		<compendium display="false" />
		<supports>Favored Enemy,Monster Type</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Giants tower over humans and their kind. They are humanlike in shape, though some have multiple heads (ettins) or deformities (fomorians). The six varieties of true giant are hill giants, stone giants, frost giants, fire giants, cloud giants, and storm giants. Besides these, creatures such as ogres and trolls are giants.</p>
		</description>		
	</element>
	<element name="Magical Beasts" type="Class Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_BEAST_MONSTROSITIES">
		<supports>Favored Enemy,Monster Type</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Magical beasts are set apart from other beasts not just by their magical nature, but by their heightened intelligence. The most iconic magical beast is the dragon, but behir, chimera, and umber hulks also fall under this type.</p>
		</description>		
	</element>
	<element name="Oozes" type="Class Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_OOZES">
		<requirements>ID_GODS_LIVING</requirements>
		<compendium display="false" />
		<supports>Favored Enemy,Monster Type</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Oozes are gelatinous creatures that rarely have a fixed shape. They are mostly subterranean, dwelling in caves and dungeons and feeding on refuse, carrion, or creatures unlucky enough to get in their way. Black puddings and gelatinous cubes are among the most recognizable oozes.</p>
		</description>		
	</element>
	<element name="Plants" type="Class Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_PLANTS">
		<requirements>ID_GODS_LIVING</requirements>
		<compendium display="false" />
		<supports>Favored Enemy,Monster Type</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Plants in this context are vegetable creatures, not ordinary flora. Most of them are ambulatory, and some are carnivorous. The quintessential plants are the shambling mound and the treant. Fungal creatures such as the gas spore and the myconid also fall into this category.</p>
		</description>		
	</element>
	<element name="Undead" type="Class Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_UNDEAD">
		<supports>Favored Enemy,Monster Type,Basic</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Undead are once-living creatures brought to a horrifying state of undeath through the practice of necromantic magic or some unholy curse. Undead include walking corpses, such as vampires and zombies, as well as bodiless spirits, such as ghosts and specters.</p>
		</description>		
	</element>
    <element name="Humanoids" type="Class Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_PHB_CLASS_FEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_HUMANOIDS_1">
        <supports>Favored Enemy,Monster Type,Basic</supports>
        <description>
            <p>Humanoids are the main peoples of the world, both civilized and savage, including humans, sleen, and a tremendous variety of other species. They have language and culture, few if any innate magical abilities (though most humanoids can learn spellcasting), and a bipedal form. The most common humanoid races are humans. Almost as numerous but far more savage and brutal, are the races of goblinoids (goblins, hobgoblins, and bugbears), orcs, gnolls, lizardfolk, and kobolds.</p>
        </description>
        <sheet display="false" />
    </element>
    <element name="Humanoids" type="Class Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_PHB_CLASS_FEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_HUMANOIDS_2">
		<compendium display="false" />
        <requirements>ID_WOTC_PHB_CLASS_FEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_HUMANOIDS_1</requirements>
        <supports>Favored Enemy,Monster Type</supports>
        <description>
            <p>Humanoids are the main peoples of the world, both civilized and savage, including humans, sleen, and a tremendous variety of other species. They have language and culture, few if any innate magical abilities (though most humanoids can learn spellcasting), and a bipedal form. The most common humanoid races are humans. Almost as numerous but far more savage and brutal, are the races of goblinoids (goblins, hobgoblins, and bugbears), orcs, gnolls, lizardfolk, and kobolds.</p>
        </description>
        <sheet display="false" />
    </element>
    <element name="Humanoids" type="Class Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_PHB_CLASS_FEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_HUMANOIDS_3">
		<compendium display="false" />
        <requirements>ID_WOTC_PHB_CLASS_FEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_HUMANOIDS_2</requirements>
        <supports>Favored Enemy,Monster Type</supports>
        <description>
            <p>Humanoids are the main peoples of the world, both civilized and savage, including humans, sleen, and a tremendous variety of other species. They have language and culture, few if any innate magical abilities (though most humanoids can learn spellcasting), and a bipedal form. The most common humanoid races are humans. Almost as numerous but far more savage and brutal, are the races of goblinoids (goblins, hobgoblins, and bugbears), orcs, gnolls, lizardfolk, and kobolds.</p>
        </description>
        <sheet display="false" />
    </element>
    <element name="Humans" type="Class Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_PHB_CLASS_FEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_HUMANOID_HUMAN">
        <supports>Humanoid Favored Enemy</supports>
        <description>
            <p>Although they lost much in the Fall, humans remain the dominant race on Tal Ahmur. Whether they seek to survive in the ruins of their once-great kingdom of Caladon, the savage frontier of the Verge, or the decadent city states of the Nightlands, humans refuse to let their time be past.</p>
        </description>
    </element>
    <element name="Dwarves" type="Class Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_PHB_CLASS_FEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_HUMANOID_DWARVES">
        <supports>Humanoid Favored Enemy</supports>
		<requirements>ID_GODS_LIVING</requirements>
		<compendium display="false" />
        <description>
            <p>Bold and hardy, dwarves are known as skilled warriors, miners, and workers of stone and metal. Though they stand well under 5 feet tall, dwarves are so broad and compact that they can weigh as much as a human standing nearly two feet taller.</p>
        </description>
    </element>
    <element name="Elves" type="Class Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_PHB_CLASS_FEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_HUMANOID_ELVES">
        <supports>Humanoid Favored Enemy</supports>
		<requirements>ID_GODS_LIVING</requirements>
		<compendium display="false" />
        <description>
            <p>Elves are a magical people of otherworldly grace, living in the world but not entirely part of it. They live in places of ethereal beauty, in the midst of ancient forests or in silvery spires glittering with faerie light, where soft music drifts through the air and gentle fragrances waft on the breeze. Elves love nature and magic, art and artistry, music and poetry, and the good things of the world.</p>
        </description>
    </element>
    <element name="Halflings" type="Class Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_PHB_CLASS_FEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_HUMANOID_HALFLINGS">
        <supports>Humanoid Favored Enemy</supports>
		<requirements>ID_GODS_LIVING</requirements>
		<compendium display="false" />
        <description>
            <p>The diminutive halflings survive in a world full of larger creatures by avoiding notice or, barring that, avoiding offense. Standing about 3 feet tall, they appear relatively harmless and so have managed to survive for centuries in the shadow of empires and on the edges of wars and political strife.</p>
        </description>
    </element>
    <element name="Dragonborn" type="Class Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_PHB_CLASS_FEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_HUMANOID_DRAGONBORN">
        <supports>Humanoid Favored Enemy</supports>
		<requirements>ID_GODS_LIVING</requirements>
		<compendium display="false" />
        <description>
            <p>It’s easy to assume that a dragonborn is a monster, especially if his or her scales betray a chromatic heritage. Unless the dragonborn starts breathing fire and causing destruction, though, people are likely to respond with caution rather than outright fear.</p>
        </description>
    </element>
    <element name="Gnomes" type="Class Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_PHB_CLASS_FEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_HUMANOID_GNOME">
        <supports>Humanoid Favored Enemy</supports>
		<requirements>ID_GODS_LIVING</requirements>
		<compendium display="false" />
        <description>
            <p>Gnomes don’t look like a threat and can quickly disarm suspicion with good humor. The common folk are often curious about gnomes, likely never having seen one before, but they are rarely hostile or fearful.</p>
        </description>
    </element>
    <element name="Half-Elves" type="Class Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_PHB_CLASS_FEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_HUMANOID_HALF_ELF">
        <supports>Humanoid Favored Enemy</supports>
		<requirements>ID_GODS_LIVING</requirements>
		<compendium display="false" />
        <description>
            <p>To humans, half-elves look like elves, and to elves, they look human. In height, they’re on par with both parents, though they’re neither as slender as elves nor as broad as humans.</p>
        </description>
    </element>
    <element name="Half-Orcs" type="Class Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_PHB_CLASS_FEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_HUMANOID_HALF_ORC">
        <supports>Humanoid Favored Enemy</supports>
		<requirements>ID_GODS_LIVING</requirements>
		<compendium display="false" />
        <description>
            <p>Half-orcs’ grayish pigmentation, sloping foreheads, jutting jaws, prominent teeth, and towering builds make their orcish heritage plain for all to see. Half-orcs stand between 6 and 7 feet tall and usually weigh between 180 and 250 pounds.</p>
            <p class="indent"></p>
        </description>
    </element>
    <element name="Tieflings" type="Class Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_PHB_CLASS_FEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_HUMANOID_TIEFLING">
        <supports>Humanoid Favored Enemy</supports>
		<requirements>ID_GODS_LIVING</requirements>
		<compendium display="false" />
        <description>
            <p>Tieflings are derived from human bloodlines, and in the broadest possible sense, they still look human. However, their infernal heritage has left a clear imprint on their appearance. Tieflings have large horns that take any of a variety of shapes - some have curling horns like a ram, others have straight and tall horns like a gazelle’s, and some spiral upward like an antelopes’ horns. They have thick tails, four to five feet long, which lash or coil around their legs when they get upset or nervous. Their canine teeth are sharply pointed, and their eyes are solid colors black, red, white, silver, or gold with no visible sclera or pupil. Their skin tones cover the full range of human coloration, but also include various shades of red. Their hair, cascading down from behind their horns, is usually dark, from black or brown to dark red, blue, or purple.</p>
        </description>
    </element>
    <element name="Aarakocra" type="Class Feature" source="Monster Manual" id="ID_WOTC_MM_CLASS_FEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_HUMANOID_AARAKOCRA">
        <supports>Humanoid Favored Enemy</supports>
        <description>
            <p>Sequestered in high mountains atop tall trees, the aarakocra, sometimes called birdfolk, evoke fear and wonder. Making aerial patrols, these reclusive humanoids guard the windy borders of their homes against any invaders.</p>
        </description>
    </element>
    <element name="Bugbears" type="Class Feature" source="Monster Manual" id="ID_WOTC_MM_CLASS_FEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_HUMANOID_BUGBEARS">
        <supports>Humanoid Favored Enemy</supports>
        <description>
            <p>Bugbears weigh in as the largest and burliest of the goblinoids. Despite their power, the brutes are surprisingly cowardly, bullying those weaker and smaller than them but avoiding more imposing targets unless they can get an advantage. Their preferred tactic is to ambush their opponents, at which they are surprisingly skilled.</p>
        </description>
    </element>
    <element name="Bullywugs" type="Class Feature" source="Monster Manual" id="ID_WOTC_MM_CLASS_FEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_HUMANOID_BULLYWUGS">
        <supports>Humanoid Favored Enemy</supports>
        <description>
            <p>Life as a bullywug is nasty, short, and wet. These frog-headed amphibious humanoids must stay constantly moist, dwelling in rainy forests, marshes, and damp caves. Always hungry and thoroughly selfish, bullywugs overwhelm opponents with superior numbers when they can, but they flee from serious threats to search for easier prey.</p>
            <p class="indent">Bullywugs have green, gray, or mottled yellow skin that shifts through shades of gray, green, and brown, allowing them to blend in with their surroundings. They wear crude armor and wield simple weapons, and can deliver a powerful bite to foes that press too close.</p>
        </description>
    </element>
    <element name="Gith" type="Class Feature" source="Monster Manual" id="ID_WOTC_MM_CLASS_FEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_HUMANOID_GITH">
        <supports>Humanoid Favored Enemy</supports>
		<supports>Humanoid Favored Enemy</supports>
		<requirements>ID_GODS_LIVING</requirements>
        <description>
            <p>The gith are a race of humanoids who have been enslaved by mind flayers for countless generations. Some sages claimed that they were once descended from humans, while others maintained that their original race was in fact unknown.</p>
        </description>
    </element>
    <element name="Gnolls" type="Class Feature" source="Monster Manual" id="ID_WOTC_MM_CLASS_FEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_HUMANOID_GNOLLS">
        <supports>Humanoid Favored Enemy</supports>
        <description>
            <p>Gnolls are feral, demon-worshipping humanoids that attack settlements along the frontiers and borderlands of civilization without warning, slaughtering their victims and devouring their flesh.</p>
        </description>
    </element>
    <element name="Grimlock" type="Class Feature" source="Monster Manual" id="ID_WOTC_MM_CLASS_FEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_HUMANOID_GRIMLOCK">
        <supports>Humanoid Favored Enemy</supports>
        <description>
            <p>The degenerate subterranean grimlocks were once human, but their worship of some unknown deity, demon, or race of other beings transformed them into blind, monstrous cannibals long ago.</p>
        </description>
    </element>
    <element name="Goblins" type="Class Feature" source="Monster Manual" id="ID_WOTC_MM_CLASS_FEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_HUMANOID_GOBLINS">
        <supports>Humanoid Favored Enemy</supports>
        <description>
            <p>Goblins are the most common type of goblin and the ones that give name to the whole race. They are small, selfish humanoids that crave power and regularly abuse whatever authority they obtain. Individually weak, they gather in large-sometimes overwhelming-numbers. Goblins possess a mysterious knack for beast mastery. They might not always tame the beasts they capture, but they often achieve success in channeling the creatures’ aggression.</p>
        </description>
    </element>
    <element name="Hobgoblins" type="Class Feature" source="Monster Manual" id="ID_WOTC_MM_CLASS_FEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_HUMANOID_HOBGOBLINS">
        <supports>Humanoid Favored Enemy</supports>
        <description>
            <p>The bellicose and militaristic hobgoblins are the most disciplined and intelligent of the goblinoids, and they often rule over goblins and bugbears. After receiving training from hobgoblins, a savage goblin tribe that raids caravans might become a disciplined invading army.</p>
        </description>
    </element>
    <element name="Kenku" type="Class Feature" source="Monster Manual" id="ID_WOTC_MM_CLASS_FEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_HUMANOID_KENKU">
		<requirements>ID_GODS_LIVING</requirements>
		<compendium display="false" />
        <supports>Humanoid Favored Enemy</supports>
		<requirements>ID_GODS_LIVING</requirements>
		<compendium display="false" />
        <description>
            <p>Kenku are feathered humanoids that wander the world as vagabonds, driven by greed. They can perfectly imitate any sound they hear.</p>
        </description>
    </element>
    <element name="Kobolds" type="Class Feature" source="Monster Manual" id="ID_WOTC_MM_CLASS_FEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_HUMANOID_KOBOLDS">
        <supports>Humanoid Favored Enemy</supports>
        <description>
            <p>Kobolds are craven reptilian humanoids that are prone to serve creatures more powerful than them as minions and toadies. They worship dragons as gods, and their natural aptitude for magic leads some sages to speculate that they might be related to them.</p>
        </description>
    </element>
    <element name="Kuo-Toa" type="Class Feature" source="Monster Manual" id="ID_WOTC_MM_CLASS_FEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_HUMANOID_KUO_TOA">
        <supports>Humanoid Favored Enemy</supports>
        <description>
            <p>Kuo-toa are degenerate fishlike humanoids that once inhabited the shores and islands of the surface world. Long ago humans and their ilk drove the kuo-toa underground. Kuo-toa worship sinister entities that live in the deep and dark places of the world.</p>
        </description>
    </element>
    <element name="Lizardfolk" type="Class Feature" source="Monster Manual" id="ID_WOTC_MM_CLASS_FEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_HUMANOID_LIZARDFOLK">
        <supports>Humanoid Favored Enemy</supports>
        <description>
            <p>Lizardfolk are primitive reptilian humanoids that lurk in the swamps and jungles of the world. Their hut villages thrive in forbidding grottos, half-sunken ruins, and watery caverns.</p>
        </description>
    </element>
    <element name="Orcs" type="Class Feature" source="Monster Manual" id="ID_WOTC_MM_CLASS_FEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_HUMANOID_ORCS">
        <supports>Humanoid Favored Enemy</supports>
        <description>
            <p>Orcs are savage raiders and pillagers with stooped postures, low foreheads, and piggish faces with prominent lower canines that resemble tusks.</p>
        </description>
    </element>
    <element name="Wereboars" type="Class Feature" source="Monster Manual" id="ID_WOTC_MM_CLASS_FEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_HUMANOID_WEREBOARS">
        <supports>Humanoid Favored Enemy</supports>
		<requirements>ID_GODS_LIVING</requirements>
		<compendium display="false" />
        <description>
            <p>Wereboars are ill-tempered and vulgar brutes. As humanoids, they are stocky and muscular, with short, stiff hair. In their humanoid and hybrid forms, they use heavy weapons, while in hybrid or animal form, they gain a devastating goring attack through which their curse is spread. A wereboar infects other creatures indiscriminately, relishing the fact that the more its victims resist the curse, the more savage and bestial they become.</p>
            <p class="indent">Wereboars live in small family groups in remote forest areas, building ramshackle huts or dwelling in caves. They are suspicious of strangers but sometimes ally themselves with orcs.</p>
        </description>
    </element>
    <element name="Wererats" type="Class Feature" source="Monster Manual" id="ID_WOTC_MM_CLASS_FEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_HUMANOID_WERERATS">
		<requirements>ID_GODS_LIVING</requirements>
		<compendium display="false" />
        <supports>Humanoid Favored Enemy</supports>
        <description>
            <p>Wererats are cunning lycanthropes with sly, avaricious personalities. They are wiry and twitchy in humanoid form, with thin hair and darting eyes. In their humanoid and hybrid forms, wererats prefer light weapons and use ambush tactics rather than fighting as a pack. Although a wererat can deliver a nasty bite in its rat form, it favors that form for stealthy infiltration and escape rather than combat.</p>
            <p class="indent">A wererat clan operates much like a thieves’ guild, with wererats transmitting their curse only to creatures they want to induct into the clan. Wererats that are accidentally cursed or break loose from the clan’s control are quickly hunted down and killed.</p>
            <p class="indent">Wererat clans are found throughout urban civilization, often dwelling in cellars and catacombs. These creatures are common in the sewers beneath major cities, viewing those subterranean areas as their hunting grounds. Rats and giant rats are commonly found living among wererats.</p>
        </description>
    </element>
    <element name="Weretigers" type="Class Feature" source="Monster Manual" id="ID_WOTC_MM_CLASS_FEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_HUMANOID_WERETIGER">
		<requirements>ID_GODS_LIVING</requirements>
		<compendium display="false" />
        <supports>Humanoid Favored Enemy</supports>
        <description>
            <p>Weretigers are ferocious hunters and warriors with a haughty and fastidious nature. Lithe and sleekly muscular in humanoid form, they are taller than average and meticulously groomed. Weretigers grow to enormous size in animal and hybrid form, but they fight in their more refined humanoid form when they can.</p>
            <p class="indent">They don’t like to pass on their curse, because every new weretiger means competition for territory and prey.</p>
            <p class="indent">Weretigers live in jungles on the fringes of humanoid civilization, traveling to isolated settlements to trade or revel. They live and hunt alone or in small family groups.</p>
        </description>
    </element>
    <element name="Lycanthropes" type="Class Feature" source="Monster Manual" id="ID_WOTC_MM_CLASS_FEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_HUMANOID_WEREWOLF">
        <supports>Humanoid Favored Enemy</supports>
        <description>
            <p>Hereditary shapeshifters, lycanthropes are feared in communities both large and small. In its natural form, a lycanthrope appears as a monstrous hybrid of human and beast, but it can choose to wear a human disguise or an animal shape.</p>
        </description>
    </element>
    <element name="Merfolk" type="Class Feature" source="Monster Manual" id="ID_WOTC_MM_CLASS_FEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_HUMANOID_MERFOLK">
        <supports>Humanoid Favored Enemy</supports>
        <description>
            <p>Aquatic humanoids with the upper body of a human and the lower body of a fish, merfolk adorn their skin and scales with shell decorations.</p>
            <p class="indent">Merfolk tribes and kingdoms span the world, and their people are as varied in color, culture, and outlook as the human races of the surface. Land folk and merfolk rarely meet except by chance, though starry-eyed mariners tell tales of romance with these creatures along the shoals of faraway islands.</p>
            <p class="indent">Merfolk lack the materials and practical means to forge weapons beneath the waves, to write books and keep lore, or to shape stone to raise buildings and cities. As a result, most live in small hunter-gatherer tribes, each of which holds unique values and creeds. Only occasionally do merfolk unite under the rule of a single leader. They do so to face a common threat or to complete a conquest. Such unifications can be the beginning of undersea kingdoms with dynasties lasting hundreds of years.</p>
        </description>
    </element>
    <element name="Quaggoths" type="Class Feature" source="Monster Manual" id="ID_WOTC_MM_CLASS_FEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_HUMANOID_QUAGGOTH">
        <supports>Humanoid Favored Enemy</supports>
        <description>
            <p>Savage and territorial, quaggoths climb the chasms of the dark caverns. They maul their foes in a frenzy, becoming even more murderous in the face of death.</p>
        </description>
    </element>
    <element name="Sahuagin" type="Class Feature" source="Monster Manual" id="ID_WOTC_MM_CLASS_FEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_HUMANOID_SAHUAGIN">
        <supports>Humanoid Favored Enemy</supports>
		<requirements>ID_GODS_LIVING</requirements>	
        <supports>Humanoid Favored Enemy</supports>
        <description>
            <p>Across fog-shrouded coasts or endless ocean swells, an ominous drone sounded on a conch shell chills the blood of all who hear it. This is the sound of the sahuagin hunting horn-a call to raid and battle. Coastal settlers refer to sahuagin as "sea devils," for sahuagin have no compassion in them, slaughtering the crews of ships and decimating coastal villages.</p>
        </description>
    </element>
    <element name="Thri-Kreen" type="Class Feature" source="Monster Manual" id="ID_WOTC_MM_CLASS_FEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_HUMANOID_THRI_KREEN">
        <supports>Humanoid Favored Enemy</supports>
		<requirements>ID_GODS_LIVING</requirements>
		<compendium display="false" />
        <description>
            <p>Thri-kreen wander the deserts and savannas of the world, avoiding all other races.</p>
        </description>
    </element>
    <element name="Troglodytes" type="Class Feature" source="Monster Manual" id="ID_WOTC_MM_CLASS_FEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_HUMANOID_TROGLODYTE">
        <supports>Humanoid Favored Enemy</supports>
        <description>
            <p>The savage, degenerate troglodytes squat in the shallow depths of the Underdark in a constant state of war against their neighbors and one another. They mark the borders of their territories with cracked bones and skulls, or with pictographs painted in blood or dung.</p>
            <p class="indent">Perhaps the most loathsome of all humanoids, troglodytes eat anything they can stomach. They dwell in filth. The walls of their cavern homes are smeared with grime, oily secretions, and the debris of their foul feasting.</p>
        </description>
    </element>
    <element name="Sleen" type="Class Feature" source="Monster Manual" id="ID_WOTC_MM_CLASS_FEATURE_RANGER_FAVORED_ENEMY_HUMANOID_YUAN_TI_PUREBLOOD">
        <supports>Humanoid Favored Enemy</supports>
        <description>
            <p>Sleen are slender humanoids with sinuous bodies and serpentine features, such as snake-like eyes, a forked tongue, and patches of scales on their skin. They’re regarded as sneaky and magical, and are popularly conceived of as a collection of thieves, sorcerers, or both.</p>
        </description>
    </element>

	<element name="Arctic" type="Class Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_NATURAL_EXPLORER_FT_ARCTIC">
		<supports>Favored Terrain</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You are particularly familiar with one type of natural environment and are adept at traveling and surviving in such regions. You gain the following benefits while in your favored terrain:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>You gain advantage on initiative rolls.</li>
				<li>You gain advantage on Dexterity saving throws.</li>
				<li>When you make an ability check related to the terrain, your proficiency bonus is doubled if you are using a skill that you’re proficient in.</li>
			</ul>
			<p class="indent">In addition, while traveling for an hour or more in your favored terrain, you also gain the following benefits:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>Difficult terrain doesn’t slow your group’s travel.</li>
				<li>Your group can’t become lost except by magical means.</li>
				<li>Even when you are engaged in another activity while traveling (such as foraging, navigating, or tracking), you remain alert to danger.</li>
				<li>If you are traveling alone, you can move stealthily at a normal pace.</li>
				<li>When you forage, you find twice as much food as you normally would.</li>
				<li>While tracking other creatures, you also learn their exact number, their sizes, and how long ago they passed through the area.</li>
			</ul>
		</description>		
	</element>
	<element name="Coast" type="Class Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_NATURAL_EXPLORER_FT_COAST">
		<supports>Favored Terrain</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You are particularly familiar with one type of natural environment and are adept at traveling and surviving in such regions. You gain the following benefits while in your favored terrain:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>You gain advantage on initiative rolls.</li>
				<li>You gain advantage on Dexterity saving throws.</li>
				<li>When you make an ability check related to the terrain, your proficiency bonus is doubled if you are using a skill that you’re proficient in.</li>
			</ul>
			<p class="indent">In addition, while traveling for an hour or more in your favored terrain, you also gain the following benefits:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>Difficult terrain doesn’t slow your group’s travel.</li>
				<li>Your group can’t become lost except by magical means.</li>
				<li>Even when you are engaged in another activity while traveling (such as foraging, navigating, or tracking), you remain alert to danger.</li>
				<li>If you are traveling alone, you can move stealthily at a normal pace.</li>
				<li>When you forage, you find twice as much food as you normally would.</li>
				<li>While tracking other creatures, you also learn their exact number, their sizes, and how long ago they passed through the area.</li>
			</ul>
		</description>		
	</element>
	<element name="Desert" type="Class Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_NATURAL_EXPLORER_FT_DESERT">
		<supports>Favored Terrain</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You are particularly familiar with one type of natural environment and are adept at traveling and surviving in such regions. You gain the following benefits while in your favored terrain:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>You gain advantage on initiative rolls.</li>
				<li>You gain advantage on Dexterity saving throws.</li>
				<li>When you make an ability check related to the terrain, your proficiency bonus is doubled if you are using a skill that you’re proficient in.</li>
			</ul>
			<p class="indent">In addition, while traveling for an hour or more in your favored terrain, you also gain the following benefits:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>Difficult terrain doesn’t slow your group’s travel.</li>
				<li>Your group can’t become lost except by magical means.</li>
				<li>Even when you are engaged in another activity while traveling (such as foraging, navigating, or tracking), you remain alert to danger.</li>
				<li>If you are traveling alone, you can move stealthily at a normal pace.</li>
				<li>When you forage, you find twice as much food as you normally would.</li>
				<li>While tracking other creatures, you also learn their exact number, their sizes, and how long ago they passed through the area.</li>
			</ul>
		</description>		
	</element>
	<element name="Forest" type="Class Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_NATURAL_EXPLORER_FT_FOREST">
		<supports>Favored Terrain</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You are particularly familiar with one type of natural environment and are adept at traveling and surviving in such regions. You gain the following benefits while in your favored terrain:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>You gain advantage on initiative rolls.</li>
				<li>You gain advantage on Dexterity saving throws.</li>
				<li>When you make an ability check related to the terrain, your proficiency bonus is doubled if you are using a skill that you’re proficient in.</li>
			</ul>
			<p class="indent">In addition, while traveling for an hour or more in your favored terrain, you also gain the following benefits:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>Difficult terrain doesn’t slow your group’s travel.</li>
				<li>Your group can’t become lost except by magical means.</li>
				<li>Even when you are engaged in another activity while traveling (such as foraging, navigating, or tracking), you remain alert to danger.</li>
				<li>If you are traveling alone, you can move stealthily at a normal pace.</li>
				<li>When you forage, you find twice as much food as you normally would.</li>
				<li>While tracking other creatures, you also learn their exact number, their sizes, and how long ago they passed through the area.</li>
			</ul>
		</description>		
	</element>
	<element name="Grassland" type="Class Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_NATURAL_EXPLORER_FT_GRASSLAND">
		<supports>Favored Terrain</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You are particularly familiar with one type of natural environment and are adept at traveling and surviving in such regions. You gain the following benefits while in your favored terrain:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>You gain advantage on initiative rolls.</li>
				<li>You gain advantage on Dexterity saving throws.</li>
				<li>When you make an ability check related to the terrain, your proficiency bonus is doubled if you are using a skill that you’re proficient in.</li>
			</ul>
			<p class="indent">In addition, while traveling for an hour or more in your favored terrain, you also gain the following benefits:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>Difficult terrain doesn’t slow your group’s travel.</li>
				<li>Your group can’t become lost except by magical means.</li>
				<li>Even when you are engaged in another activity while traveling (such as foraging, navigating, or tracking), you remain alert to danger.</li>
				<li>If you are traveling alone, you can move stealthily at a normal pace.</li>
				<li>When you forage, you find twice as much food as you normally would.</li>
				<li>While tracking other creatures, you also learn their exact number, their sizes, and how long ago they passed through the area.</li>
			</ul>
		</description>		
	</element>
	<element name="Mountain" type="Class Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_NATURAL_EXPLORER_FT_MOUNTAIN">
		<supports>Favored Terrain</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You are particularly familiar with one type of natural environment and are adept at traveling and surviving in such regions. You gain the following benefits while in your favored terrain:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>You gain advantage on initiative rolls.</li>
				<li>You gain advantage on Dexterity saving throws.</li>
				<li>When you make an ability check related to the terrain, your proficiency bonus is doubled if you are using a skill that you’re proficient in.</li>
			</ul>
			<p class="indent">In addition, while traveling for an hour or more in your favored terrain, you also gain the following benefits:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>Difficult terrain doesn’t slow your group’s travel.</li>
				<li>Your group can’t become lost except by magical means.</li>
				<li>Even when you are engaged in another activity while traveling (such as foraging, navigating, or tracking), you remain alert to danger.</li>
				<li>If you are traveling alone, you can move stealthily at a normal pace.</li>
				<li>When you forage, you find twice as much food as you normally would.</li>
				<li>While tracking other creatures, you also learn their exact number, their sizes, and how long ago they passed through the area.</li>
			</ul>
		</description>		
	</element>
	<element name="Swamp" type="Class Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_NATURAL_EXPLORER_FT_SWAMP">
		<supports>Favored Terrain</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You are particularly familiar with one type of natural environment and are adept at traveling and surviving in such regions. You gain the following benefits while in your favored terrain:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>You gain advantage on initiative rolls.</li>
				<li>You gain advantage on Dexterity saving throws.</li>
				<li>When you make an ability check related to the terrain, your proficiency bonus is doubled if you are using a skill that you’re proficient in.</li>
			</ul>
			<p class="indent">In addition, while traveling for an hour or more in your favored terrain, you also gain the following benefits:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>Difficult terrain doesn’t slow your group’s travel.</li>
				<li>Your group can’t become lost except by magical means.</li>
				<li>Even when you are engaged in another activity while traveling (such as foraging, navigating, or tracking), you remain alert to danger.</li>
				<li>If you are traveling alone, you can move stealthily at a normal pace.</li>
				<li>When you forage, you find twice as much food as you normally would.</li>
				<li>While tracking other creatures, you also learn their exact number, their sizes, and how long ago they passed through the area.</li>
			</ul>
		</description>		
	</element>
	<element name="Underground" type="Class Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_CLASSFEATURE_RANGER_NATURAL_EXPLORER_FT_UNDERDARK">
		<supports>Favored Terrain</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You are particularly familiar with one type of natural environment and are adept at traveling and surviving in such regions. You gain the following benefits while in your favored terrain:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>You gain advantage on initiative rolls.</li>
				<li>You gain advantage on Dexterity saving throws.</li>
				<li>When you make an ability check related to the terrain, your proficiency bonus is doubled if you are using a skill that you’re proficient in.</li>
			</ul>
			<p class="indent">In addition, while traveling for an hour or more in your favored terrain, you also gain the following benefits:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>Difficult terrain doesn’t slow your group’s travel.</li>
				<li>Your group can’t become lost except by magical means.</li>
				<li>Even when you are engaged in another activity while traveling (such as foraging, navigating, or tracking), you remain alert to danger.</li>
				<li>If you are traveling alone, you can move stealthily at a normal pace.</li>
				<li>When you forage, you find twice as much food as you normally would.</li>
				<li>While tracking other creatures, you also learn their exact number, their sizes, and how long ago they passed through the area.</li>
			</ul>
		</description>		
	</element>

	<element name="Hunter" type="Archetype" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_ARCHETYPE_RANGER_HUNTER">
		<supports>Ranger Archetype</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Emulating the Hunter archetype means accepting your place as a bulwark between civilization and the terrors of the wilderness. As you walk the Hunter’s path, you learn specialized techniques for fighting the threats you face, from rampaging ogres and hordes of orcs to towering giants and terrifying dragons.</p>
			<div element="ID_WOTC_ARCHETYPEFEATURE_RANGER_HUNTERS_PREY" />
			<div element="ID_WOTC_ARCHETYPEFEATURE_RANGER_DEFENSIVE_TACTICS" />
			<div element="ID_WOTC_ARCHETYPEFEATURE_RANGER_MULTIATTACK" />
			<div element="ID_WOTC_ARCHETYPEFEATURE_RANGER_SUPERIOR_HUNTERS_DEFENSE" />
		</description>
		<sheet display="false">
			<description>Emulating the Hunter archetype means accepting your place as a bulwark between civilization and the terrors of the wilderness.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_WOTC_ARCHETYPEFEATURE_RANGER_HUNTERS_PREY" level="3" />
			<grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_WOTC_ARCHETYPEFEATURE_RANGER_DEFENSIVE_TACTICS" level="7" />
			<grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_WOTC_ARCHETYPEFEATURE_RANGER_MULTIATTACK" level="11" />
			<grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_WOTC_ARCHETYPEFEATURE_RANGER_SUPERIOR_HUNTERS_DEFENSE" level="15" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Hunter’s Prey" type="Archetype Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_ARCHETYPEFEATURE_RANGER_HUNTERS_PREY">
		<description>
			<p>At 3rd level, you gain one of the following features of your choice.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Colossus Slayer.</em></strong> Your tenacity can wear down the most potent foes. When you hit a creature with a weapon attack, the creature takes an extra 1d8 damage if it’s below its hit point maximum. You can deal this extra damage only once per turn.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Giant Killer.</em></strong> When a Large or larger creature within 5 feet of you hits or misses you with an attack, you can use your reaction to attack that creature immediately after its attack, provided that you can see the creature.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Horde Breaker.</em></strong> Once on each of your turns when you make a weapon attack, you can make another attack with the same weapon against a different creature that is within 5 feet of the original target and within range of your weapon.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<rules>
			<select type="Archetype Feature" name="Hunter’s Prey" supports="Hunters Pray" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Defensive Tactics" type="Archetype Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_ARCHETYPEFEATURE_RANGER_DEFENSIVE_TACTICS">
		<description>
			<p>At 7th level, you gain one of the following features of your choice.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Escape the Horde.</em></strong> Opportunity attacks against you are made with disadvantage.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Multiattack Defense.</em></strong> When a creature hits you with an attack, you gain a +4 bonus to AC against all subsequent attacks made by that creature for the rest of the turn.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Steel Will.</em></strong> You have advantage on saving throws against being frightened.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<rules>
			<select type="Archetype Feature" name="Defensive Tactics" supports="Defensive Tactics" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Multiattack" type="Archetype Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_ARCHETYPEFEATURE_RANGER_MULTIATTACK">
		<description>
			<p>At 11th level, you gain one of the following features of your choice.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Volley.</em></strong> You can use your action to make a ranged attack against any number of creatures within 10 feet of a point you can see within your weapon’s range. You must have ammunition for each target, as normal, and you make a separate attack roll for each target.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Whirlwind Attack.</em></strong> You can use your action to make a melee attack against any number of creatures within 5 feet of you, with a separate attack roll for each target.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<rules>
			<select type="Archetype Feature" name="Multiattack" supports="Multiattack" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Superior Hunter’s Defense" type="Archetype Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_ARCHETYPEFEATURE_RANGER_SUPERIOR_HUNTERS_DEFENSE">
		<description>
			<p>At 15th level, you gain one of the following features of your choice.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Evasion.</em></strong> You can nimbly dodge out of the way of certain area effects, such as a red dragon’s fiery breath or a lightning bolt spell. When you are subjected to an effect that allows you to make a Dexterity saving throw to take only half damage, you instead take no damage if you succeed on the saving throw, and only half damage if you fail.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Stand Against the Tide.</em></strong> When a hostile creature misses you with a melee attack, you can use your reaction to force that creature to repeat the same attack against another creature (other than itself) of your choice.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Uncanny Dodge.</em></strong> When an attacker that you can see hits you with an attack, you can use your reaction to halve the attack’s damage against you.</p>		
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<rules>
			<select type="Archetype Feature" name="Superior Hunter’s Defense" supports="Superior Hunters Defense" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Colossus Slayer" type="Archetype Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_ARCHETYPEFEATURE_RANGER_HUNTERS_PREY_COLOSSUS_SLAYER">
		<supports>Hunters Pray</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Your tenacity can wear down the most potent foes. When you hit a creature with a weapon attack, the creature takes an extra 1d8 damage if it’s below its hit point maximum. You can deal this extra damage only once per turn.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet usage="1/Turn">
			<description>When you hit a creature with a weapon attack, the creature takes an extra 1d8 damage if it’s below its hp maximum.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Giant Killer" type="Archetype Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_ARCHETYPEFEATURE_RANGER_HUNTERS_PREY_GIANT_KILLER">
		<supports>Hunters Pray</supports>
		<description>
			<p>When a Large or larger creature within 5 feet of you hits or misses you with an attack, you can use your reaction to attack that creature immediately after its attack, provided that you can see the creature.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet action="Reaction">
			<description>When a Large or larger creature within 5 feet of you hits or misses you with an attack, you can use your reaction to attack that creature immediately after its attack, provided that you can see the creature.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Horde Breaker" type="Archetype Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_ARCHETYPEFEATURE_RANGER_HUNTERS_PREY_HORDE_BREAKER">
		<supports>Hunters Pray</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Once on each of your turns when you make a weapon attack, you can make another attack with the same weapon against a different creature that is within 5 feet of the original target and within range of your weapon.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>Once on each of your turns when you make a weapon attack, you can make another attack with the same weapon against a different creature that is within 5 feet of the original target and within range of your weapon.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	
	<element name="Escape the Horde" type="Archetype Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_ARCHETYPEFEATURE_RANGER_DEFENSIVE_TACTICS_ESCAPE_THE_HORDE">
		<supports>Defensive Tactics</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Opportunity attacks against you are made with disadvantage.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>Opportunity attacks against you are made with disadvantage.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Multiattack Defense" type="Archetype Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_ARCHETYPEFEATURE_RANGER_DEFENSIVE_TACTICS_MULTIATTACK_DEFENSE">
		<supports>Defensive Tactics</supports>
		<description>
			<p>When a creature hits you with an attack, you gain a +4 bonus to AC against all subsequent attacks made by that creature for the rest of the turn.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>When a creature hits you with an attack, you gain a +4 bonus to AC against all subsequent attacks made by that creature for the rest of the turn.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Steel Will" type="Archetype Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_ARCHETYPEFEATURE_RANGER_DEFENSIVE_TACTICS_STEEL_WILL">
		<supports>Defensive Tactics</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You have advantage on saving throws against being frightened.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>You have advantage on saving throws against being frightened.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	
	<element name="Volley" type="Archetype Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_ARCHETYPEFEATURE_RANGER_MULTIATTACK_VOLLEY">
		<supports>Multiattack</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You can use your action to make a ranged attack against any number of creatures within 10 feet of a point you can see within your weapon’s range. You must have ammunition for each target, as normal, and you make a separate attack roll for each target.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet action="Action">
			<description>You can make a ranged attack against any number of creatures within 10 feet of a point you can see within your weapon’s range. You must have ammunition for each target, as normal, and you make a separate attack roll for each target.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Whirlwind Attack" type="Archetype Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_ARCHETYPEFEATURE_RANGER_MULTIATTACK_WHIRLWIND_ATTACK">
		<supports>Multiattack</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You can use your action to make a melee attack against any number of creatures within 5 feet of you, with a separate attack roll for each target.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet action="Action">
			<description>You can make a melee attack against any number of creatures within 5 feet of you, with a separate attack roll for each target.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>

	<element name="Evasion" type="Archetype Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_ARCHETYPEFEATURE_RANGER_SUPERIOR_HUNTERS_DEFENSE_EVASION">
		<supports>Superior Hunters Defense</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You can nimbly dodge out of the way of certain area effects, such as a red dragon’s fiery breath or a lightning bolt spell. When you are subjected to an effect that allows you to make a Dexterity saving throw to take only half damage, you instead take no damage if you succeed on the saving throw, and only half damage if you fail.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>When you are subjected to an effect that allows you to make a Dexterity saving throw to take only half damage, you instead take no damage if you succeed on the saving throw, and only half damage if you fail.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Stand Against the Tide" type="Archetype Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_ARCHETYPEFEATURE_RANGER_SUPERIOR_HUNTERS_DEFENSE_STAND_AGAINST_THE_TIDE">
		<supports>Superior Hunters Defense</supports>
		<description>
			<p>When a hostile creature misses you with a melee attack, you can use your reaction to force that creature to repeat the same attack against another creature (other than itself) of your choice.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet action="Reaction">
			<description>When a hostile creature misses you with a melee attack, you can force that creature to repeat the same attack against another creature of your choice.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Uncanny Dodge" type="Archetype Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_ARCHETYPEFEATURE_RANGER_SUPERIOR_HUNTERS_DEFENSE_UNCANNY_DODGE">
		<supports>Superior Hunters Defense</supports>
		<description>
			<p>When an attacker that you can see hits you with an attack, you can use your reaction to halve the attack’s damage against you.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet action="Reaction">
			<description>When an attacker that you can see hits you with an attack, you can halve the attack’s damage against you.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>

	<element name="Beast Master" type="Archetype" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_ARCHETYPE_RANGER_BEAST_MASTER">
		<supports>Ranger Archetype</supports>
		<description>
			<p>The Beast Master archetype embodies a friendship between the civilized races and the beasts of the world. Through training and spiritual communion, beast and ranger learn to work as one, determined to fight the monstrous foes that threaten civilization and the wilderness alike. Emulating the Beast Master archetype means committing yourself to this ideal, working in partnership with an animal as its companion and friend.</p>
			<div element="ID_WOTC_ARCHETYPEFEATURE_RANGER_RANGERS_COMPANION" />
			<div element="ID_WOTC_ARCHETYPEFEATURE_RANGER_EXCEPTIONAL_TRAINING" />
			<div element="ID_WOTC_ARCHETYPEFEATURE_RANGER_BESTIAL_FURY" />
			<div element="ID_WOTC_ARCHETYPEFEATURE_RANGER_SHARE_SPELLS" />
		</description>
		<sheet display="false">
			<description>The Beast Master archetype embodies a friendship between the civilized races and the beasts of the world.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_WOTC_ARCHETYPEFEATURE_RANGER_RANGERS_COMPANION" level="3" />
			<grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_WOTC_ARCHETYPEFEATURE_RANGER_EXCEPTIONAL_TRAINING" level="7" />
			<grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_WOTC_ARCHETYPEFEATURE_RANGER_BESTIAL_FURY" level="11" />
			<grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_WOTC_ARCHETYPEFEATURE_RANGER_SHARE_SPELLS" level="15" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Ranger’s Companion" type="Archetype Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_ARCHETYPEFEATURE_RANGER_RANGERS_COMPANION">
		<description>
			<p>At 3rd level, you learn to use your magic to create a powerful bond with a creature of the natural world. This ritual requires the expenditure of 50 gp worth of rare herbs and fine food, as well as 8 hours of spiritual communion, training, joint hunting, and other forms of bonding.</p>
			<p>You normally select your companion from among the following animals: an <em>ape</em>, a <em>black bear</em>, a <em>boar</em>, a <em>giant badger</em>, a <em>giant weasel</em>, a <em>mule</em>, a <em>panther</em>, or a <em>wolf</em>. However, your DM may allow for different animals, or may pick an animal for you based on the surrounding terrain and on what types of creatures would logically be present in the area.</p>
			<p>If the selected animal is not present at the start of the ritual, it will be called forth from the wild and appear shortly after the ritual has begun. At the end of the ritual it gains all the benefits listed below. You can have only one animal companion at a time.</p>
			<p class="indent">The companion is completely devoted to you and obeys your commands as best it can. It rolls for initiative separately and is nominally controlled by the DM, but you can determine its actions, decisions, attitudes, and so on when desired, as long as you are present and conscious. If left to its own device, the companion will focus on protecting you and itself. While traveling through your favored terrain with only the companion, you can move stealthily at a normal pace (as if you were alone).</p>
			<p class="indent">Your animal companion increases in strength as you level. It uses your proficiency bonus rather than its own, and adds its proficiency bonus to its AC and damage rolls. It also becomes proficient with all saving throws. Lastly, your animal companion has a number of hit dice equal to your level, which will determine its hit points as normal.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>The companion obeys your commands as best as it can. It acts on its own initiative. While traveling through your favored terrain with only the companion, you can move stealthily at a normal pace. You can obtain a new companion by spending 50 gp worth of rare herbs and food and 8 hours in a bonding ritual. You can only have one animal companion at a time.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<select type="Companion" name="Ranger’s Companion" requirements="![level:15]" supports="Ranger,Beast,(Tiny||Small||Medium),(1/4||1/8||0)" />
			<stat name="additional:hp:max" value="companion:hplevel" level="3"/>
			<stat name="additional:hp:max" value="companion:hplevel" level="4"/>
			<stat name="additional:hp:max" value="companion:hplevel" level="5"/>
			<stat name="additional:hp:max" value="companion:hplevel" level="6"/>
			<stat name="additional:hp:max" value="companion:hplevel" level="7"/>
			<stat name="additional:hp:max" value="companion:hplevel" level="8"/>
			<stat name="additional:hp:max" value="companion:hplevel" level="9"/>
			<stat name="additional:hp:max" value="companion:hplevel" level="10"/>
			<stat name="additional:hp:max" value="companion:hplevel" level="11"/>
			<stat name="additional:hp:max" value="companion:hplevel" level="12"/>
			<stat name="additional:hp:max" value="companion:hplevel" level="13"/>
			<stat name="additional:hp:max" value="companion:hplevel" level="14"/>
			<stat name="companion:hp:max" value="additional:hp:max" />
			<stat name="companion:ac" value="proficiency" bonus="proficiency"/>
			<stat name="companion:proficiency" value="proficiency" bonus="base"/>
			<stat name="companion:proficiency" value="-2"/>
			<stat name="companion:strength:save:proficiency" value="companion:proficiency" bonus="proficiency" />
			<stat name="companion:dexterity:save:proficiency" value="companion:proficiency" bonus="proficiency" />
			<stat name="companion:constitution:save:proficiency" value="companion:proficiency" bonus="proficiency" />
			<stat name="companion:intelligence:save:proficiency" value="companion:proficiency" bonus="proficiency" />
			<stat name="companion:wisdom:save:proficiency" value="companion:proficiency" bonus="proficiency" />
			<stat name="companion:charisma:save:proficiency" value="companion:proficiency" bonus="proficiency" />
			<!-- PRIMAL -->
			<select type="Companion" name="Ranger’s Companion" requirements="[level:15]" supports="Ranger,Beast,(Large),(6)" />
			<stat name="additional:hp:max" value="companion:hplevel" level="3"/>
			<stat name="additional:hp:max" value="companion:hplevel" level="4"/>
			<stat name="additional:hp:max" value="companion:hplevel" level="5"/>
			<stat name="additional:hp:max" value="companion:hplevel" level="6"/>
			<stat name="additional:hp:max" value="companion:hplevel" level="7"/>
			<stat name="additional:hp:max" value="companion:hplevel" level="8"/>
			<stat name="additional:hp:max" value="companion:hplevel" level="9"/>
			<stat name="additional:hp:max" value="companion:hplevel" level="10"/>
			<stat name="additional:hp:max" value="companion:hplevel" level="11"/>
			<stat name="additional:hp:max" value="companion:hplevel" level="12"/>
			<stat name="additional:hp:max" value="companion:hplevel" level="13"/>
			<stat name="additional:hp:max" value="companion:hplevel" level="14"/>
			<stat name="additional:hp:max" value="companion:hplevel" level="15"/>
			<stat name="additional:hp:max" value="companion:hplevel" level="16"/>
			<stat name="additional:hp:max" value="companion:hplevel" level="17"/>
			<stat name="additional:hp:max" value="companion:hplevel" level="18"/>
			<stat name="additional:hp:max" value="companion:hplevel" level="19"/>
			<stat name="additional:hp:max" value="companion:hplevel" level="20"/>			
			<stat name="companion:hp:max" value="additional:hp:max" />
			<stat name="companion:ac" value="proficiency" bonus="proficiency"/>
			<stat name="companion:proficiency" value="proficiency" bonus="base"/>
			<stat name="companion:proficiency" value="-2"/>
			<stat name="companion:strength:save:proficiency" value="companion:proficiency" bonus="proficiency" />
			<stat name="companion:dexterity:save:proficiency" value="companion:proficiency" bonus="proficiency" />
			<stat name="companion:constitution:save:proficiency" value="companion:proficiency" bonus="proficiency" />
			<stat name="companion:intelligence:save:proficiency" value="companion:proficiency" bonus="proficiency" />
			<stat name="companion:wisdom:save:proficiency" value="companion:proficiency" bonus="proficiency" />
			<stat name="companion:charisma:save:proficiency" value="companion:proficiency" bonus="proficiency" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Primal Infusion" type="Archetype Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_ARCHETYPEFEATURE_RANGER_EXCEPTIONAL_TRAINING">
		<description>
			<p>Beginning at 7th level, your primal magic suffuses the animal companion at your side. It gains advantage on all saving throws, it adds your Wisdom modifier to its attack rolls, and its attacks count as magical for the purpose of overcoming resistance and immunity to nonmagical attacks and damage.</p>
			<p>In addition, if your animal companion is ever slain, the magical bond you share now allows you to return it to life. With 8 hours of meditation and the expenditure of 50 gp worth of rare herbs, you call forth your companion’s spirit and use your magic to create a new body for it. You can return an animal companion to life in this manner even if you do not possess any part of its body.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>You can return your companion to life when slain by spending 50 gp worth of rare herbs and 8 hours of meditation.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Protective Fury" type="Archetype Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_ARCHETYPEFEATURE_RANGER_BESTIAL_FURY">
		<description>
			<p>Beginning at 11th level, your animal companion can fly into a protective rage when its allies are threatened. When an ally of your companion is struck by a critical hit or any other attack that reduces them below half of their maximum hit points, the animal companion can use its reaction to enter a protective rage. If it does, it gains the following benefits:</p>
			<ul>
			<li>It gains resistance to all damage, with the exception of necrotic damage.</li>
			<li>It can attack twice, instead of once, whenever it takes the attack action on its turn.</li>
			<li>Any targets of the companion's attacks become <em>threatened</em> until the start of the companion's next turn. A threatened creature suffers disadvantage on any attack made against a target other than the companion.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>This rage lasts for 1 minute. After it has been used, your companion cannot rage again until it has performed a short or long rest.</p>			
		</description>
		<sheet display="false">
			<description>When an ally of your companion is struck by a critical hit or any other attack that reduces them below half of their maximum hit points, your companion can use its reaction to enter a protective rage, gaining the following benefits: it gains resistance to all damage except necrotic, can make two attacks on its turn, and any targets of its attacks become <em>threatened</em> until the start of the companion's next turn (threatened creatures suffer disadvantage on attacks made against targets other than the companion). This rage lasts for 1 minute. After it has been used, your companion cannot rage again until it has performed a short or long rest.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Primal Manifestation" type="Archetype Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_ARCHETYPEFEATURE_RANGER_SHARE_SPELLS">
		<description>
			<p>Beginning at 15th level, your animal companion grows in size and manifests primal markings indicative of its mystical power. It gains the following benefits:</p>
			<ul>
			<li>Its size increases by one category (usually from medium to large).</li>
			<li>Its Strength score increases by 4. All other ability scores increase by 2.</li>
			<li>Its hit and damage dice both increase to the next highest die size (so d6 becomes d8, etc.).</li>
			<li>Its speed increases by 10 feet.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>Recalculate hit points, attacks, skills, and ability DCs as needed.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false">
			<description>Your animal companion has grown in size and power, and its traits have been increased.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
</elements>